[
    {
        "question": "Which organization signed an MoU with REMC Limited to explore financing options for power projects for Railways?",
        "options": [
            "Power Finance Corporation (PFC)",
            "Rural Electrification Corporation (REC)",
            "Indian Railway Finance Corporation (IRFC)",
            "NTPC Limited",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Indian Railway Finance Corporation (IRFC)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the RBI's 15-day credit score update rule:\n1. Lenders are mandated to update credit bureau records every 15 days.\n2. The rule enhances borrowers' credit visibility by promptly reflecting repayments and missed payments.\n3. This system aims to replace the yearly update system, effective from January 1, 2025.\nWhich of the following options is correct?",
        "options": [
            "Only 1",
            "Only 1 and 2",
            "Only 1 and 3",
            "Only 2 and 3",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Only 1 and 2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which researcher from the Zoological Survey of India (ZSI) is credited with discovering the new species of pangolin, named the Indo-Burmese pangolin (Manis indoburmanica), in Arunachal Pradesh?",
        "options": [
            "Lenrik Konchok",
            "Suresh Naik",
            "Ramesh Pandey",
            "Deepa Sharma",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the capital of Nicaragua, where India and Nicaragua recently signed an MoU for Quick Impact Projects?",
        "options": [
            "Managua",
            "San Salvador",
            "Tegucigalpa",
            "Bogotá",
            "Harare"
        ],
        "answer": "Managua"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the title of Lt Gen Kanwal Jeet Singh Dhillon's debut book that won the Crossword Books Award?",
        "options": [
            "The Balakot Strikes",
            "Behind Enemy Lines: Balakot Dhua Dhua Ho Gye",
            "Kitne Ghazi Aaye Kitne Ghazi Gaye",
            "The Kashmir Chronicles: The Untold Stories",
            "Trial and Error"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who will receive the Lifetime Achievement Award at the 77th Annual Directors Guild of America (DGA) Awards, and what makes their contributions significant?",
        "options": [
            "Steven Spielberg; known for his blockbuster films and innovative techniques",
            "Ang Lee; recognized for his diverse filmmaking and cinematic excellence",
            "Martin Scorsese; celebrated for his contribution to crime and drama genres",
            "Ridley Scott; honored for his work in science fiction and historical epics",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of India's first indigenous macrolide antibiotic, which aims to address antimicrobial resistance (AMR)?",
        "options": [
            "Nafithromycin",
            "Amoxyclav",
            "Ciprofloxacin",
            "Doxycycline",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "Nafithromycin"
    },
    {
        "question": "Parliament passed the Bharatiya Vayuyan Vidheyak 2024. Which old act does the Bharatiya Vayuyan Vidheyak 2024 replace?",
        "options": [
            "Indian Aviation Act, 1920",
            "Civil Aviation Act, 1950",
            "Aeronautics Act, 1945",
            "Aircraft Act, 1934",
            "Airplane Act, 1999"
        ],
        "answer": "Aircraft Act, 1934"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which position did IIT Kharagpur secure in India in the QS World University Rankings Sustainability 2025?",
        "options": [
            "1st",
            "2nd",
            "3rd",
            "5th",
            "6th"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "What mandate has the RBI issued regarding RTGS and NEFT transactions by April 1, 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Enable free cross-border fund transfers.",
            "Implement a beneficiary account name lookup feature for free.",
            "Increase the transaction limit for RTGS and NEFT transfers.",
            "Launch a new digital payment platform for RTGS and NEFT.",
            "Both 3 & 4"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization approved a grant of 25.45 million US dollars to the Solomon Islands for the development of sustainable water supply and sanitation services?",
        "options": [
            "Asian Development Bank (ADB)",
            "World Bank",
            "International Monetary Fund (IMF)",
            "New Development Bank",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Asian Development Bank (ADB)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Union Minister recently unveiled the Anna Chakra, designed to optimize logistics under the Public Distribution System (PDS) and the SCAN Portal, which automates subsidy claim submissions and settlements under the National Food Security Act (NFSA) for faster processing?",
        "options": [
            "Shri Rajnath Singh",
            "Shri Pralhad Joshi",
            "Shri Nitin Gadkari",
            "Shri Piyush Goyal",
            "Shri Jagdeep Dhankar"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the recent United Nations report on drylands, what percentage of Earth's land has become drier over the last 30 years?",
        "options": [
            "45%",
            "55%",
            "77%",
            "88%",
            "99%"
        ],
        "answer": "77%"
    },
    {
        "question": "India has surpassed $1 trillion in Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) from April 2000 to September 2024. How much of this FDI has been recorded since 2014, reflecting a 119% increase over the previous decade?",
        "options": [
            "$500.2 billion",
            "$667.4 billion",
            "$805.9 billion",
            "$1 trillion",
            "$904.9 billion"
        ],
        "answer": "$667.4 billion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company won two awards at the 3rd PSU Transformation Awards 2024 for Innovative Product Development and Technology Adoption?",
        "options": [
            "Cochin Shipyard Limited",
            "Hindustan Shipyard Limited",
            "Mazagon Dock Shipbuilders Limited",
            "Garden Reach Shipbuilders & Engineers",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Hindustan Shipyard Limited"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who became the shortest-serving Prime Minister in the history of the French Fifth Republic after being defeated in a confidence vote in December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Emmanuel Macron",
            "Michel Barnier",
            "Marine Le Pen",
            "Jean-Luc Mélenchon",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "Michel Barnier"
    },
    {
        "question": "The International Gita Mahotsav 2024 was inaugurated in which Indian state?",
        "options": [
            "Rajasthan",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Haryana",
            "Gujarat",
            "Madhya Pradesh"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "India received the ISSA Good Practice Award for Asia-Pacific 2024 for which purpose?",
        "options": [
            "Launching a nationwide pension scheme",
            "Enhancing agricultural productivity",
            "Innovative activities of the Employees' Provident Fund Organisation (EPFO)",
            "Advancing renewable energy technologies",
            "Developing multilingual education platforms"
        ],
        "answer": "Innovative activities of the Employees' Provident Fund Organisation (EPFO)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the new Chairperson of NABL, succeeding Prof. Subbanna Ayyappan?",
        "options": [
            "Dr. Sandip Shah",
            "Dr. Subbanna Ayyappan",
            "Prof. Rajesh Kumar",
            "Dr. Ramesh Patel",
            "Prof. Brijesh Khaitan"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Sandip Shah"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country did INS Sarvekshak conduct a joint hydrographic survey with, focusing on maritime infrastructure, resource management, and coastal planning?",
        "options": [
            "India",
            "Mauritius",
            "Maldives",
            "Sri Lanka",
            "Madagascar"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following payment systems saw a growth in transaction volume in November compared to October 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Unified Payments Interface (UPI)",
            "Immediate Payment Service (IMPS)",
            "FASTag",
            "Aadhaar Enabled Payment System (AePS)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the new Managing Director (MD) and Chief Executive Officer (CEO) of J&K Bank, effective December 30, 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Baldev Prakash",
            "Amitava Chatterjee",
            "Dinesh Khara",
            "Rajnish Kumar",
            "Shamsheer Mattoo"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the new Chairperson of the National Human Rights Commission (NHRC) in December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Justice Arun Kumar Mishra",
            "Justice H.L. Dattu",
            "Justice K.G. Balakrishnan",
            "Justice V. Ramasubramanian",
            "Justice D.Y. Chandrachud"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Jamsetji Tata Award for pioneering the biosciences movement in India?",
        "options": [
            "Ratan Tata",
            "Janak Kumar Mehta",
            "Kiran Mazumdar-Shaw",
            "B Muthuraman",
            "Adar Poonawala"
        ],
        "answer": "Kiran Mazumdar-Shaw"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the World Chess Championship Game 14, GM D. Gukesh became the youngest World Chess Champion, surpassing the record of __________.",
        "options": [
            "Magnus Carlsen",
            "Ding Liren",
            "Viswanathan Anand",
            "Garry Kasparov",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the reason for the RBI imposing penalties on Manappuram Finance and IndusInd Bank?",
        "options": [
            "Failure to maintain minimum capital adequacy ratios",
            "Inadequate reporting of non-performing assets (NPAs)",
            "Violation of foreign exchange management laws",
            "Non-compliance with regulations, including verification of customer PAN",
            "Both 1 & 2"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization signed an agreement with Silizium Circuits Pvt Ltd for the \"Design and Development of LEO Satellite Components and GNSS RF Front End ASIC\"?",
        "options": [
            "Centre for Development of Telematics (C-DOT)",
            "Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO)",
            "National Informatics Centre (NIC)",
            "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)",
            "NPCI"
        ],
        "answer": "Centre for Development of Telematics (C-DOT)"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the India State of Forest Report 2023, by how much has India's forest cover increased since 2021?",
        "options": [
            "1,000 sq. km",
            "1,445 sq. km",
            "2,000 sq. km",
            "800 sq. km",
            "777 sq. km"
        ],
        "answer": "1,445 sq. km"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following organization has adopted 02 December as the International Day for the Abolition of Slavery?",
        "options": [
            "World Labour Organization",
            "United Nations General Assembly",
            "World Bank",
            "International Red Cross Society",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "United Nations General Assembly"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which bird was officially declared the national bird of the United States, symbolizing American strength and freedom since 1782?",
        "options": [
            "Peregrine Falcon",
            "Golden Eagle",
            "American Robin",
            "Bald Eagle",
            "White Pigeon"
        ],
        "answer": "Bald Eagle"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Tikhir Tribe, which held its first-ever Log Drum Pulling Ceremony during the 25th Hornbill Festival 2024, is indigenous to which Indian state?",
        "options": [
            "Assam",
            "Nagaland",
            "Manipur",
            "Arunachal Pradesh",
            "Meghalaya"
        ],
        "answer": "Nagaland"
    },
    {
        "question": "SheSTEM 2024, an initiative of the India-Nordic BEST project, focused on which key area for energy solutions?",
        "options": [
            "Solar Power & Wind Energy",
            "Battery Technology and Energy Storage",
            "Hydroelectric Power & Semiconductors",
            "AI in Satellite Communication System",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "Battery Technology and Energy Storage"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the new CEO of DBS Bank India, effective March 1, 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Surojit Shome",
            "Rajat Verma",
            "Piyush Gupta",
            "Gautam Jain",
            "Vedant Mahajan"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "M.D.R Ramachandran, who recently passed away, was the Chief Minister of which State/Union Territory?",
        "options": [
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Lakshadweep",
            "Puducherry",
            "Kerala",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country is set to allow visa-free entry for Indian tourists starting March 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Japan",
            "Russia",
            "Canada",
            "Germany",
            "China"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where will the 2025 Para Athletics World Championships be hosted in India?",
        "options": [
            "Mumbai",
            "Bengaluru",
            "Delhi",
            "Hyderabad",
            "Chennai"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where is the Gympie-Gympie plant, the World's Most Toxic Plant, scientifically known as Dendrocnide moroides, native to?",
        "options": [
            "Africa",
            "South America",
            "Australia",
            "Southeast Asia",
            "North America"
        ],
        "answer": "Australia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who did Anahat Singh defeat in the final to win her 9th PSA Challenger title at the Western India Slam 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Amneeshenraj Chandaran",
            "Akanksha Salunkhe",
            "Deepika Pallikal",
            "Joshna Chinappa",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who posthumously honored Dr. Vishakha Tripathi Ji with the Lifetime Achievement Award for her extraordinary service to humanity?",
        "options": [
            "World Health Organization (WHO)",
            "Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR)",
            "United Nations Development Program (UNDP)",
            "Asia Pacific Vascular Society (APVS)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary age group targeted by HDFC SKY's newly launched Youth Plan?",
        "options": [
            "16 to 22 years",
            "18 to 25 years",
            "20 to 30 years",
            "21 to 28 years",
            "18 to 30 years"
        ],
        "answer": "18 to 25 years"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Indian Navy's latest survey ship, Nirdeshak, will be commissioned at which location?",
        "options": [
            "Mumbai",
            "Chennai",
            "Kochi",
            "Visakhapatnam",
            "Kolkata"
        ],
        "answer": "Visakhapatnam"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following Central Armed Police Forces celebrated its 60th raising day in December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Central Reserve Police Force",
            "Border Security Force",
            "Sashastra Seema Bal",
            "Indo-Tibetan Border Police",
            "CISF"
        ],
        "answer": "Border Security Force"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which word was named Oxford Word of the Year 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Screen Fatigue",
            "Digital Burnout",
            "Information Overload",
            "Brain Rot",
            "Rizz"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many children received the Pradhan Mantri Rashtriya Bal Puraskar from President Murmu in December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "10 children",
            "17 children",
            "20 children",
            "27 children",
            "37 children"
        ],
        "answer": "17 children"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Indira Gandhi Prize for Peace, Disarmament, and Development 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Ban Ki-moon",
            "Angela Merkel",
            "Veronica Michelle Bachelet",
            "Jacinda Ardern",
            "Malala Yousafzai"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was crowned Miss India USA 2024 at the event held in New Jersey?",
        "options": [
            "Nirali Desia",
            "Manini Patel",
            "Sanskriti Sharma",
            "Caitlin Sandra Neil",
            "Shipra Negi"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "From which sector did the Government withdraw the windfall tax as announced in December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Renewable Energy Sector",
            "Aviation and Oil Sector",
            "Telecommunications Sector",
            "Electric Automobile Manufacturing Sector",
            "Real Estate"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "By which name was Tulsi Gowda, the renowned environmentalist who recently passed away, popularly known?",
        "options": [
            "The Green Crusader",
            "Mother of Trees",
            "Forest Guardian of India",
            "Encyclopedia of the Forest",
            "Mother Nature"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the gross direct tax collection for 2024-25 as of December 17?",
        "options": [
            "₹15.82 lakh crore",
            "₹18.56 lakh crore",
            "₹19.21 lakh crore",
            "₹20.45 lakh crore",
            "₹24.57 lakh crore"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was awarded the Indian Film Personality of the Year at the 55th International Film Festival of India (IFFI)?",
        "options": [
            "Amitabh Bachchan",
            "Rajinikanth",
            "Vikrant Massey",
            "Nawazuddin Siddiqui",
            "Deepika Padukone"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    }
]